Ford, Ruth mss., 1936-1986 LMC 2757
Lilly Library
Ford, Ruth mss.
1936-1986
Lilly Library
Ford, Ruth, 1911-2009
LMC 2757
2 Boxes 2 standard
The Ford, Ruth mss., 1936-1986 consists of the papers of stage and screen actress Ruth Ford.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Ruth Ford was born on July 7, 1911 in Brookhaven, Mississippi to Charles and Gertrude Cato Ford. Her parents owned and managed hotels in several southern towns; as a result Ford and her brother, the poet, novelist and surrealist artist, Charles Henri Ford, spent much of their childhood moving from hotel to hotel. Ford married Goetz (Peter) Van Eyck in the 1940s but the marriage soon ended in divorce. In 1950, she married actor Zachary Scott and they remained together until his death in 1965.
After joining her brother in New York City in the 1930s, Ford modeled for well-known professional photographers Carl Van Vechten, Man Ray and Cecil Beaton, whose photos appeared in magazines such as Vogue, Mademoiselle and Harper's. In 1938, she performed in "The Shoemaker's Holiday," a production of Orson Welles' Mercury Theater Group. Subsequently moving to Hollywood, she made approximately two dozen B-movies, including The Gorilla Man and Lady Gangster. She was later to remark that she "made so many terrible movies in Hollywood." Returning to New York City, Ford experienced greater success in the theater. An acquaintance of William Faulkner's since their days in Mississippi, in 1959 she starred in the well-reviewed title role of Temple Drake in Faulkner's play, Requiem for a Nun. She went on to work in the Broadway theater and in television productions. She died in New York City on August 12, 2009 at the age of 98.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into the following series: I. Correspondence; II. Miscellaneous.
Scope and Content Note
Collection consists of the papers of stage and screen actress Ruth Ford. Correspondents include Elre Eick, John Huston, Jørgen Roos, Goetz (Peter) Van Eyck. Miscellaneous materials include a typescript of an untitled original treatment written by John Huston and Ruth Marton (i.e., Ruth Ford).
Acquisition Information
Acquired: 2011
Theater; Ford, Ruth, 1911-2009 --Correspondence.; Huston, John, 1906-1987.; Roos, Jørgen, 1922-1998.; Eyck, Peter van, 1911-1969.
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent
  - Eick, Elre to Ford, Ruth, 1936-1941 (Box 1)
  - Eick, Elre to Van Eyck, Goetz, 1936-1937; undated (Box 1)
  - Ford, Ruth to Van Eyck, Goetz, 1936; (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Ford, Ruth to Van Eyck, Goetz, 1937; (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Ford, Ruth to Van Eyck, Goetz, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Ford, Ruth to Van Eyck, Goetz, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Ford, Ruth to Van Eyck, Goetz, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Ford, Ruth to Van Eyck, Goetz, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Ford, Ruth to Van Eyck, Goetz, undated (Box 1)
  - Ford, Ruth to Roos, Jørgen, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Huston, John to Ford, Ruth, 1958-1986 (Box 1)
  - Jones, Nancy to Van Eyck, Goetz, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Roos, Jørgen to Ford, Ruth, 1949-1984 (Box 1)
  - Tyler, Parker to Ford, Ruth, 1943-1978 (Box 1)
  - Van Blöme, Edgar Adolf to Van Eyck, Goetz, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Van Eyck, Goetz to Ford, Ruth, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Van Eyck, Goetz to Ford, Ruth, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Van Eyck, Goetz to Ford, Ruth, 1938-1941 (Box 2)
  - Van Eyck, Goetz to Ford, Ruth, 1942 (Box 2)
  - Van Eyck, Goetz to Ford, Ruth, 1943-1944 (Box 2)
  - Van Eyck, Goetz to Ford, Ruth, 1945-1946 (Box 2)
  - Van Eyck, Goetz to Ford, Ruth, 1947-1950 (Box 2)
  - Van Eyck, Goetz to Ford, Ruth, undated (Box 2)
  - Van Eyck, Goetz to unidentified correspondent, 1945 (Box 2)
  - Van Eyck, Goetz to Van Eyck, Shelley, 1944-1947 (Box 2)
  - [Brother of Van Eyck] to Van Eyck, Goetz, 1937 (Box 2)
  - de Vilaine, G. to Van Eyck, Goetz, 1939-1940 (Box 2)
  - [Unknown last name], Camille to Van Eyck, Goetz, 1937 (Box 2)
  - Unidentified correspondents to Van Eyck, Goetz (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - Untitled Original, co-written by John Huston and Ruth Marton (i.e., Ruth Ford), typescript (Box 2)
  - Invitations and magazine clipping (Box 2)